Dr. Carlos Peralta

Atmospheric and data scientist. Geospatial analyst.



cperalta@protonmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/carlos9917 https://github.com/carlos9917

SUMMARY

Mathematical modeller and data scientist with an academic background in theoretical physics, applying my skills and experience to a wide variety of data science problems. A very diverse professional and personal background developed my ability to learn, adapt and solve problems in innovative ways. Extensive experience in data simulation, modelling, analysis and visualisation.

WORK EXPERIENCE

CURRENT, FROM NOV 2018 (FT)

Danish Meteorological Institute Senior Scientist in NWP

Produced climate projections for The Arctic and Denmark. Developed GIS software for shadows of obstacles near the roads to improve road weather prediction. Developed and optimized operational verification tool for deterministic and probabilistic forecasts. Developed visualizations for weather and verification scores. Monitoring and display of model production, post-processing of climate data

JUL 2015 - OCT 2018 (FT)

Enercon

Developer for meteorological simulations

Developed software for wind energy using CFD, weather models (WRF), and data processing. Data engineering of wind and weather data. Worked on wind power forecasting. Provided customer support, developed tailored weather forecasts and data visualizations

JUL 2011 - JUN 2015 (FT)

Fraunhofer Institute for Wind Energy Research Scientist

Developed multiple CFD solvers and turbulent-modelling libraries in OpenFOAM. Wrote meteorological software for external clients. Developed scripts for post-processing meteorological data. Participated in

lications

AUG 2009 - JUN 2011 (FT)

German Weather Service (DWD) Research Scientist

Developed first version of initial condition perturbations for operational ensemble system. Evaluated and verified probabilistic forecasts. Participated in international project meetings and conferences, wrote reports and publications.

international project meetings and conferences, wrote reports and pub-

JUN 2002 – AUG 2007 (FT)

Astrophysics Group. University of Melbourne Doctoral and Postdoctoral researcher

Proposed turbulent flow as a cause of timing irregularities in pulsars. Discovered timing irregularities in pulsars follow an avalanche process.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy 2007

> Astrophysics group. School of Physics University of Melbourne

Master of Science in Physics 2002

> Department of Physics University of Oriente

Bachelor of Science in Physics 1997

> CUM LAUDE Department of Physics University of Oriente

AWARDS

2002-2007 Melbourne Postgraduate Scholarship

University of Melbourne

Manuel Peñalver Award - Physics 1991-1997

University of Oriente

COMPUTER SKILLS

PROGRAMMING Fortran, C, C++, shell scripting

Python,R,Julia

Matplotlib, QGIS, NCL, Grads, DATA VISUALIZATION

Bokeh, Plotly, Streamlit, Shiny

SQL,pandas,numpy,scipy,scikit-learn DATA SCIENCE/ML

keras,tensorflow,pytorch

tidyverse,dplyr

MS Office, Libreoffice, Latex WORD PROCESSING

> Git, CICD, Docker, kubernetes DEVOPS

> > Airflow, GCP

WEATHER MODELS COSMO,WRF,Harmonie,ECMWF

DATA STORAGE FORMATS NetCDF,GRIB,BUFR

COMMUNICATION SKILLS

Spanish (native) LANGUAGES

> English/German (fluent) Swedish (proficient)

Author/co-author of 55 papers, **PUBLICATIONS**

reports and conference proc. Energies editorial board

EDITORIAL ACTIVITIES Reviewer of CFD/weather journals

Supervised 6 master students STUDENT SUPERVISION

3 interns, 1 PhD student

SKILLS

Multidisciplinarity

I have considerable experience in working in an international and multidisciplinary environment. I speak three languages fluently. My record also shows that I am able to move effectively between fields. This provides me with the skills to quickly adapt to new working environments and to efficiently tackle new challenges.

Passionate

I became interested in natural sciences from an early age and my education and research cemented this interest into a passion for problem solving. I enjoy analyzing and visualizing data, understanding patterns and trends and applying computer simulations and machine learning methods to real life problems.

Data science

Hands on experience as data engineer, data pipelines maintenance and acquisition/processing of terabyte-sized weather data from heterogeneous sources (used for example on operational meteorology). Extensive experience using data science applied to geospatial problems.

COURSES

Machine Learning Zoomcamp (2022). Online machine learning zoomcamp with Alex Grigorev. Practical projects with scikit learn, deep learning.

Applied Machine Learning in Python. Coursera/University of Michigan, (2018). Fundamentals of machine learning. Supervised and unsupervised machine learning. Model evaluation.

Wind Energy. Coursera/Technical University of Denmark (2015). Fundamentals of wind energy. Wind profiles, wind resource assessment. The economics of wind farms.

Managing big data with MySQL. Coursera/Duke University (2016). Fundamentals of SQL. Data aggregation, subqueries and derived tables. General MySQL fundamentals.

Machine Learning. Coursera (2015). Machine learning course with Andrew Ng.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Yang, X., Amstrup, B., Peralta, C. and Hintz, K. (2022). Danish Regional Reanalysis. Scientific Report for year 2021. DMI report 22-13

Toja-Silva, F., Konno, T., Peralta, C., Lopez-Garcia, O. and Chen, Jia (2018). A review of computational fluid dynamics (CFD) simulations of the wind flow around buildings for urban wind energy exploitation. J. of Wind Eng. and Ind. Aerodyn. 180

Peralta, C., Ben-Bouallegue, Z., Theis, S. E., Gebhardt, C. and Buchhold, M.(2012). Accounting for initial condition uncertainties in COSMO-DE-EPS. J. of Geoph. Res. Atmospheres,117, Do7108

For a complete list see my researchgate profile

SELECTED PRESENTATIONS

Accounting for temporal phase errors in the verification of surface parameters with the HARMONIE-AROME model. European Meteorological Society Annual Meeting. Copenhagen, Denmark (2019)

Topographic Effects on the Wakes of a Large Wind Farm. German Wind Energy Conference, DEWEK. Bremen, Germany (2015)

Accounting for analysis uncertainties in COSMO-DE-EPS. Joint SRNWP Workshop on Data Assimilation and Ensemble Prediction Systems. Bologna, Italy (2011)